<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to the speech or decalration [sic] of the great Turk, Sulton Mahomet Which he sent to Leopold Emperor of Germany. And is a defence of the true Christian religion against the said Turks antichristian speech. And a testimony for the Lord Jesus Christ. This was written, by George Fox, five years since, being 1683. And is it now a true prophesie, and fulfilled on the Great Turk Sulan Mahomet? who was removed and put out of his high throne the year 1687. With allowance.</title>
            <title>Answer to the speech or declaration of the great Turk, Sulton Mahomet.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1746</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835192</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835192</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39868</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70068)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1616:5, 1881:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to the speech or decalration [sic] of the great Turk, Sulton Mahomet Which he sent to Leopold Emperor of Germany. And is a defence of the true Christian religion against the said Turks antichristian speech. And a testimony for the Lord Jesus Christ. This was written, by George Fox, five years since, being 1683. And is it now a true prophesie, and fulfilled on the Great Turk Sulan Mahomet? who was removed and put out of his high throne the year 1687. With allowance.</title>
                  <title>Answer to the speech or declaration of the great Turk, Sulton Mahomet.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold, by A. Sowle, at the Three Keys in Nags-Head Court in Grace-Church-Street, over against the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A Christian apologia in which Fox proves the Sultan's positions inalid from an Islamic point of view.</note>
                  <note>Identified on UMI microfilm (Early English books, 1641-1700) reel 1881 as  A3448A (number cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Harvard University Library, and the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mehmed --  IV, --  Sultan of the Turks, 1642-1693 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Islam --  Doctrines --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39868:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39868:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To The <hi>Speech or Decalration</hi> Of the Great Turk, <hi>Sulton Mahomet.</hi> WHICH He ſent to <hi>Leopold</hi> Emperor of <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND Is a Defence of the true Chriſtian Religion againſt the ſaid <hi>Turks</hi> Antichriſtian Speech. AND A Teſtimony for the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was Written, by <hi>George Fox,</hi> five Years ſince, being <hi>1683.</hi> And is it not now a true Propheſie, and fulfilled on the Great Turk <hi>Sultan Mahomet?</hi> who was removed and put out of his high Throne the Year <hi>1687.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed, and Sold, by <hi>A. Sowle,</hi> at the <hi>Three Keys</hi> in <hi>Nags Head Court,</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Conduit</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:39868:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:39868:2"/>
            <head>The Speech or Declaration of <hi>Sultan Mahomet</hi> the great <hi>Turk.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Which he ſent to the Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> Dated <hi>March</hi> 25th 1683. from <hi>Adrianople,</hi> juſt after the Baron <hi>Saphonara</hi> the Emperor's Ambaſſador had his laſt Audience of the Prince <hi>Viries,</hi> wherein the ſaid Ambaſſador could not comply to the Extravagant Demands of the <hi>Turk;</hi> which cauſed the ſaid Grand Seignior to tranſmit the ſame to his Imperial Majeſty, which is faithfully tranſlated out of <hi>High Dutch.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>MAHOMET the fourth, Son of Emperors, and of the Famous and Renowned God; Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> King of <hi>Greece, Macedonia, Molda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Hegha;</hi> King of great and leſſer <hi>Aegypt;</hi> King of all the Inhabitants of the Earth, and Prince of the Earthly Paradice; acknowledged Prince and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Son of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> preſerver of the Cities of <hi>Hungaria;</hi> Poſſeſſor of the Sepulchre of your God; Lord of all the Emperors of the World, from the riſing of the Sun, to the going down thereof: King of all Kings, Lord of the Tree of Life, Conqueror of the <hi>Malonian Hegley,</hi> and the City <hi>Prokenix;</hi> the great Perſecutor of the Chriſtians and all wicked people, joy of the flouriſhing World, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander and Guardian of your Crucified God, Lord of the multitude of the Heathens: We Command ye to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39868:3"/>
Greet the Emperor <hi>Leopold,</hi> in caſe he deſire it, and you are a Friend to our Majeſty whoſe Power and Will we have extended very far.</p>
            <p>You have for ſome time paſt acted to our prejudice, and violated our Friendſhip; tho we have not offended you either by War or otherwiſe, yet you have taken ſecret ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice with other Kings, and your Councils, how to ſhake off your yoke; in which you have proceeded very indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly; and thereby you have expoſed your people to fear and danger, who have nothing to expect now but Death, which you have brought upon your ſelves; for I declare I will make my ſelf your Maſter, and purſue you from the Eaſt to the Weſt, and extend my Majeſty to the End of the Earth: in the procedure of all which you ſhall find my Power exerted to your extream prejudice, and ſhall feel the dreadful effects of my Wrath; and ſince you have put your hope in the ſtrength of ſome Towns and Caſtles, I have given Command to overthrow them, and trample under my Horſes feet all that is delightful to you, leaving no room hereafter to make friendſhip with me, or ſuffer you any fortified place to remain to put your truſt in; for I have reſolved forth-with to deſtroy you and your people, and to diſploy you of the <hi>German</hi> Empire after my will, Leaving in the Empire a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my dreadful Sword, that it may publickly appear that I will eſtabliſh my Religion therein, and purſue your Crucified God: whoſe Wrath I fear not, nor his coming to defend, or deliver you out of my hands; but will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn your Sacred Prieſts to the Plough, and ſuffer the Breaſts of your wives to be ſuckt by Dogs and Beaſts; you will do well to forſake your Religion, otherwiſe I will give Order to Conſume you with Fire: This is enough to let you underſtand my will; if you will be ſo wiſe as to know it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:39868:3"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to the Speech or Declaration or the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sultan Mahomet,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Find in a Paper, (which is ſaid to be thy Declaration) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, to <hi>Leopold,</hi> the German Emperor, dated the 25. of <hi>March</hi> 1683. viz.</p>
            <p>Firſt, thou ſayſt, Thou art a <hi>Poſſeſſor of the Sepulcre of your God</hi> (to wit, the Chriſtians) And that thou art a <hi>great Perſecuter of the Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Thou ſays, Thou art <hi>Lord of all the Emperors of the World, from the Riſing of the Sun to the going down thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thou ſayſt, Thou art <hi>King of all Kings, and Lord of the Tree of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Thou ſayſt, Thou art <hi>Commander: and Guardian of your Crucified God</hi> (to wit the Chriſtians) and thou ſayſt, Thou wilt <hi>purſue your Crucified God, whoſe Wrath I fear not, nor his coming to defend or deliver you out of my hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, here is Something in anſwer to the Words of <hi>Sultan Mahomet</hi> the Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> ſaying, He is a great Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor of the Chriſtians; But let him take heed, for, the Great God that made him, and Heaven, and Earth, and the Sea, and all things therein, who is Lord, Creator, and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and beholds all his Words, Wayes, Thoughts, and Actions, and all Mens and Womens upon the Earth; Neither is there any Creature that is not manifeſt in Gods Sight; But all things are naked and open unto the Eyes of him, with whom we have to do, who are the true Chriſtians in Scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who do fear, ſerve, and worſhip the Great God that made us, who is a conſuming Fire to the Wicked; and whereſoever Men do turn themſelves, there the Face of God will meet them; his Divinity extends through the whole World; Therefore you are to fear his Divine Majeſty, as you do confeſs in your Alcoran; for the Great God, the Creator of all doth know all in the Heavens, and in the Earth, both what is done in Secreet and Openly, and all is naked before him, who will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39868:4"/>
every Man, and Woman, according to their words and works, whether they be good or evil, for God is a conſuming Fire to the Wicked, and who ſhall dwell with everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but the Juſt and Holy?</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith in his Alcoran <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 34. That Jeſus ſaid, <q>Who ſhall ſuſtain the Law of God in my abſence; and the Apoſtles anſwered him, we will ſuſtain the Law of God in thy abſence, and that Jeſus ſhall be a Witneſs in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt ſuch that obey not his Law, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſee how you Turks do obey the Law or Command of Jeſus, for Jeſus ſaith, <hi>Love yuor Enemies, Bleſs them that Curſe you, do good to them that hate you, pray for them that deſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you, that you may be the Children of your Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Chriſtians were the <hi>Turks</hi> Enemies, according to the Command and Law of Jeſus, the <hi>Turks,</hi> are to Love and Bleſs them that Curſe them, and to do good to them, that hate them, and pray for them that deſpitefully uſe them and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them; ſo then the <hi>Turks</hi> are not to be Perſecutors, if they do obey the Command of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and if they be the Children of God the Father which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>But the Emperour of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſaith, he is a great Perſecutor of the Chriſtians; and you ſay in your <hi>Alcoran, That Jeſus ſhall be a Witneſs in the day of Judgment againſt ſuch that obey not his Law?</hi> Are not your own Words in your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and the Lord Jeſus, and the Apoſtles of Jeſus, Who ſhould ſuſtain the Law of God in Jeſus abſence, witneſs againſt you, who are Haters and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, inſtead of loving Enemies, according to the Command or Law of Jeſus? And therefore as <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Jeſus, ſhall be a Witneſs in the day of Judgment againſt ſuch as obey not his Law:</hi> So according to your own <hi>Alcoran,</hi> you <hi>Turks,</hi> and all others, that are Perſecutors, who diſobey the Law of Jeſus, he will be a Witneſs againſt you in the day of Judgment; yea, I ſay againſt you <hi>Turks,</hi> and all other Perſecutors upon the Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Sultan Mahomet</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſaith, he is <hi>Lord of all the Emperors of the World, from the riſing of the Sun to the going down thereof, King of all Kingr, and Lord of the Tree of Life.</hi> But are there not many Kingdoms and Kings in this Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39868:4"/>
part of the World, and many Emperors and Heathen Kings in <hi>America,</hi> and alſo in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies?</hi> Hath not the <hi>Great Mogul</hi> many Kingdoms under him? beſides <hi>Preſtor John</hi> (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſo called) hath not he many Kingdoms under him? And doth not the Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi> know, that theſe Kingdoms and Empires he is neither King nor Emperor over? Yet he ſaith, he is <hi>Emperor over all the Earth, from the riſing of the Sun to the going down thereof.</hi> Which World he knows is but his own Country, and from the riſing of the Sun in it, to the ſetting of the Sun in it; for the Sun riſeth and ſets in <hi>America,</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and all other parts of the World where he hath no Rule nor Power; and how long he may have Rule and Power, <note place="margin">Writ five Years ſince, and is he not out of his Throne now?</note>and be Emperor in his own Country God knows. And therefore it is beſt for the Emperor of the <hi>Terks</hi> to be humble, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit himſelf with an high and ambitious Mind, that he is King of Kings, and Emperor of the World where he is not, and where God hath given him no Power, leaſt the Almighty God do abaſe him, and take away his Power which he hath given him: For <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Nebuchadnezer</hi> the Emperor, <hi>That he ſhould eat Graſs like an Ox,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>till he knew that the moſt high God ruleth in the Kingdoms of Men, and giveth them to whom ſoever he will, and his Kingdom ſhould be ſure to him after that he knew that the Moſt High did Rule.</hi> And therefore the Unchangeable God, Man muſt Fear, for Heaven is his Throne, and the Earth is his Footſtool, that Earth that the <hi>Turks</hi> and all Men ſtand and walk upon: And ſo from the Face of the Eternal God and his Footſtool, cannot the <hi>Turk,</hi> nor any other Man or Woman turn themſelves, but there the Face of God will meet them; for Gods Divinity extends through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Earth, who inhabits Eternity, and dwels with an humble Heart; who beholds the Proud and Lofty afar off, and brings down the high Looks, and abaſeth the Pride of Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And again, <hi>Sultan Mahomet,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> thou ſayeſt, thou art, <hi>Lord of the Tree of Life.</hi> But the Turkiſh Emperor muſt know he is not Lord of the Tree of Life, which beareth twelve manner of Fruits, and yeildeth her Fruits every Month, and the Leaves of the Tree were for the healing of the Nations: We do not believe that the Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:39868:5"/>
hath any ſuch natural Tree, in all his Land or Garden, that yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth twelve manner of Fruits every Month, the Leaves of which are for the healing of Nations; this Tree of Life the <hi>Turks</hi> have no Power over, and <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that kept the Law or Command of <hi>Jeſus, Jeſus</hi> ſpeak to him and ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his Commandments, that they may have right to the Tree of Life, that they may enter through the Gates of the City,</hi> Namely, Heavenly and Holy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which deſcends out of Heaven from God, which is not outward <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> as in the <hi>Revelations</hi> of <hi>John</hi> the 21 and 22 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters— And <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to <hi>John</hi> his Apoſtle, <hi>He that overcometh I will give him to eat of the Tree of Life;</hi> Namely, he that overcomes the Devil, Sin and Unrighteouſneſs, whoſe Name is written in the Book of Life hath right to eat of the Tree of Life — But if that the Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi> doth not overcome, with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God and his Power, the Devil and his Works, Sin and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he cannot eat of the Tree of Life; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is not like to Lord, and to have Power over this Tree of Life, which he cannot eat of, except with the Power and Spirit of God he overcome the Devil and his Works.</p>
            <p>And concerning the Pure Religion and the Falſe, <hi>James,</hi> who was one of the APoſtles of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any Man ſeems to be Religious and bridles not his Tongue, but deceives his own Heart, that Mans Religion is vain.</hi> Therefore what Religion ſo ever the Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſet up or profeſs, or any Man or Weman elſe in the whole World, and bridle not their Tongues with Gods Power and Spirit, according to the Law or Command of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> which he gave to the Apoſtles, their Religion is vain, and they do but deceive their own Hearts with their vain Religion, from their unbridled Tongues; for pure Religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, <hi>To Viſit the Fatherleſs and the Widows in their Affliction, and to keep themſelves <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpotted from the World.</hi> And this is the pure Religion that God and Chriſt Jeſus ſet up, and his Apoſtles preach't and declared to Men, and all the Believers and Converted to God and Chriſt, and that keep their Command, did and do walk in this pure Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, Sultan Mahomet</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> Thou ſayeſt, Thou art <hi>Commander of the Chriſtians Crucifyed God;</hi> and ſayeſt,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39868:5"/>
thou wilt <hi>Purſue their Crucified God, whoſe Wrath thou feareſt not, nor his coming to defend or deliver them out of thy Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Theſe high Words are not ſpoken in the fear of God, for if thou kneweſt God thou wouldſt know his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who was made of the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the Fleſh, and declared to be the Son of God according to the Spirit of Holineſs, by the Reſurrection from the Dead; ſo that thou haſt neither Power over his God-head nor his Fleſh. And <hi>Mahomet</hi> confeſſes in his <hi>Alcoran, That</hi> Jeſus <hi>the Son of</hi> Mary <hi>is full of Light</hi> (which is according to Antient Scriptures) <hi>and of the Goſpel, to conduct People the right Way; with a confirmation of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to guide and inſtruct the Righteous</hi> — Now <hi>Mahomet</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> who make this Confeſſion in your <hi>Alcoran,</hi> then you muſt believe the Old Teſtament, and the Goſpel of the New con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> and of the Seed of <hi>David,</hi> according to the Fleſh; and that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> came according to the promiſe of God to his Prophets, who was Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Mahomet</hi> in his <hi>Alcoran</hi> confeſſes, <hi>That</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>was not begotten by the will of Man, who was conceived of</hi> Mary, <hi>and that ſhe ſhould conceive, and bring forth without the touching of Man.</hi> I ſay, the Angel of God ſaid to <hi>Mary, He was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and ſo called the Son of God: And <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Alcoran,</hi> Page 30. Chap. 33. <hi>That</hi> John <hi>did affirm Chriſt to be the</hi> Meſſiah, <hi>and to be the Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the <hi>Turks</hi> do believe this which <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Alcoran,</hi> then you muſt believe what <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith of himſelf, and the Angel of God, and what the Apoſtle ſaith of him, <hi>John</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and God was the Word, and all things were made by the Word, and without him was not any thing made that was made; and in the Word was Life, and the Life was the Light of Men, and that was the true Light which enlightens every Man that comes into the World.</hi> Now here is the Divine Light which is the Life in Chriſt, the Word by which all things were made, which enlightens every Man that comes into the World, to their Salvation if they believe in the Light, and to their Condemnation if they hate the Light: And <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>This Word was made Fleſh, and dwelt amongſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39868:6"/>
us, and his Apoſtles beheld his Glory, as the Glory of the only begotten of the Father, full of Grace and Truth, and of his fulneſs they did receive Grace for Grace;</hi> and ſaith, <hi>The Law came by</hi> Moſes, <hi>but Grace and Truth by</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now whereas the Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he is Commander and Guardian of the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>Crucified God.</hi> Now in this he is miſtaken, for the Eternal, Incomprehenſible, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, Everlaſting God, whoſe Divinity extends throughout the whole Earth, who is God in Heaven above, and in the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, to whom all Nations are but as the Drop of a Bucket; this is the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> God, whom they Serve and Worſhip in his Spirit and Truth, which the <hi>Jews</hi> did not Crucifie, nor could they Crucifie; and it is Blaſphemy for the <hi>Jews</hi> or any to ſay, That they did Crucifie the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Eternal Inviſible God, and great Ignorance for any to ſay, That the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> God was Crucified, or that the Eternal, Incomprehenſible, Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal God, the Creator of all, who is the God of the Spirits of all Fleſh, and the Breath of all Mankind is in his Power, ſo that poor Mortals or Externals ſhould ſay, think or imagine, that the Eternal, Inviſible, Everlaſting, Immortal, Incomprehenſible God was or can be Crucified, which they cannot comprehend, which is the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> God.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which was made of the Seed of <hi>David,</hi> according to the Fleſh, who took not upon him the Nature of Angels, but the Seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> He Suffered for us in the Fleſh. And ſo as <hi>Chriſt</hi> alſo hath once Suffered for Sins in the Fleſh, he the Juſt for the Unjuſt, that Chriſt might bring us to God; ſo God was not Crucified, but Chriſt being put to Death or Crucified in the Fleſh, but quickened again in the Spirit, and roſe again, and ſits at the right Hand of God; this <hi>Peter</hi> (one of the Apoſtles of <hi>Jeſus</hi>) teſtifieth, and the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> now believe it, and though <hi>Chriſt</hi> was Crucified through Weakneſs, that is through the Fleſh, yet he is alive and liveth by the Power of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. So it is clear that the Eternal and Inviſible, Incomprehenſible God was not, nor cannot be Crucified, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Son of God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered according to the Fleſh, not in his God-head: So <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed for our Sins, according to the Scripture of the Old and New Teſtament, <hi>For as in</hi> Adam <hi>all dyed, ſo even in</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſhall all be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39868:6"/>
made alive, and that Chriſt by the Grace of God ſhould taſte Death for every Man:</hi> So it was not the Inviſible, Eternal, Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible God that was Crucified and Dyed, and did taſte Death for every Man, but Chriſt according to the Fleſh, who was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to take away our Sin, and in him there was no Sin; ſo Chriſt was manifeſt to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, and Chriſt through his Death deſtroys Death that Sin brought, and the Devil the Power of Death; <hi>And about the ninth hour</hi> (when <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hanged upon the Croſs) <hi>He cryed with a loud Voice, ſaying, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</hi> So it is clear, the Eternal God did not Dye, nor was Crucified, but Chriſt was put to Death in the Fleſh; this teſtifies <hi>Mathew,</hi> one of Chriſts Apoſtles: ſo he was the one Offering, who made an end of all the Offerings among the <hi>Jews,</hi> through the offering up of the Body of <hi>Jeſus</hi> once for all; ſo the Man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> offered up himſelf one Sacrifice for Sins; ſo by that one Offering he hath perfected forever them that are Sanctified; ſo he is the Propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation Offering and Sacrifice for the Sins of the whole World, yea <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> which was of the Seed of <hi>David;</hi> and ſo according to the Scripture <hi>Chriſt</hi> Dyed for our Sins, and he was buried, and roſe again the third Day, according to the Scriptures; and after he was riſen from the Dead he was ſeen of the twelve Apoſtles, and again He was ſeen of above five hundred Brethren at once, that were Believers in him, and this was after he was Dead, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and Riſen; but none of the Princes of the World knew him, for had they known Chriſt they would not have Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him, but we know now, that Chriſt being raiſed from the Dead dies no more, and Death hath no more Dominion over Chriſt, in that he died unto Sin, and for the Sins of the whole World; but now he being raiſed from the Dead, he is ſet at the right Hand of God; and therefore <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> a Man appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of God by Miracles, Wonders and Signs which God did by him, this <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Mary</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> with their wicked hands did take, Crucified and Slay; but it was God who looſed the Pangs of Death, becauſe it was not poſſible that he ſhould be holden of it, and though the <hi>Jews</hi> did Crucifie <hi>Jeſus</hi> &amp; Slew him, and Hanged him on a Tree, yet God hath raiſed him up the third Day, and God hath Exalted him at his right Hand to be a Prince and a Saviour, to give Repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and forgiveneſs of Sins; and ſo Chriſts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39868:7"/>
Apoſtles were Witneſſes, how God raiſed him from the Dead; ſo you may here ſee, it was not God that was Crucified and Dyed, for he raiſed Chriſt from the Dead on the third Day, and ſhewed him openly to his Apoſtles, and they did Eat and Drink with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> after that God had raiſed him up from the Dead, and he commanded his Apoſtles to Preach to the People, and teſtifie, that it was he which was ordained of God to be Judge of Quick and Dead, and to him give all the Prophets (and the Apoſtles) of God witneſs, That though the Name of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> whoſoever believed in him ſhould receive remiſſion of Sins, neither is there Salvation in any other, for there is no Name under Heaven given amongſt Men whereby we muſt be ſaved, but by the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> whom the <hi>Jews</hi> Crucified, whom God hath raiſed from the Dead; for God ſaid to <hi>David, That of the Fruit of his Loynes</hi> (according to the Fleſh) <hi>God would raiſe up Chriſt to ſit on his Throne.</hi> And <hi>David,</hi> he ſeeing this before, ſpoke of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, <hi>That his Soul was not left in Hell, neither did his Fleſh ſee Corruption:</hi> So though the <hi>Jews</hi> Crucified him, and a Souldier thruſt his Speer into his Side; and though he was Crucified and hanged on a Tree, and Slain, Dead and Buried, him did God raiſe up the third Day, and he appeared to his Apoſtles and Diſciples, and did Eat and Drink with them after he was Riſen, who were the faithful Witneſſes, That God raiſed him up from the Dead, who is aſcended up into Heaven, at the right Hand of God, who being the brightneſs of Gods Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Subſtance, and upholding all things by the Word of his Power, when he had by himſelf purged our Sins, ſat down at the right Hand of the Majeſty on High, whom the Heavens, muſt receive until the times of reſtitution of all things, which God hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Mouth of all his Holy Prophets, ſince the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and he that deſcended is the ſame alſo that aſcended far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things, who led Captivity Captive, and gave Gifts unto Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And we have Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from Chriſts Blood, even Forgiveneſs of our Sins, who hath delivered us from the Devil, the Power of Darkneſs, who is the Seed of the Woman, which bruiſeth the old Serpents Head which deceived <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> which God promiſed to <hi>Adam?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39868:7"/>
That the Seed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpents Head;</hi> in which Seed, <hi>viz, Chriſt,</hi> all Nations are Bleſſed, who is the Image of the inviſible God, the firſt born of every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for by him were all things Created that are in the Heaven, and that are in the Earth, viſible and inviſible, whether they be Thrones, or Dominions, Principalities or Powers; all things were created by him, and for him, and he was before all things, and by him all things conſiſts, and Chriſt ſaid in his prayer to his Father, <hi>This is Eternal Life, that they might know thes the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi> And Jeſus deſired of God his Father ſaying, <hi>That thoſe whom God hath given him, might be with him, where he was, that they might behold his Glory which God hath given him;</hi> for he loved him before the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the World, therefore ſaith Chriſt; <hi>now, O Father, Glorifie thou me, with thy own ſelf, with the Glory which I had with thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World was;</hi> and Chriſt ſaid to his Diſcples, after he was riſen from the Dead, <hi>All Power in Heaven and in Earth is given unto me;</hi> and he bid his Diſciples, go into all the World, and Preach the Goſpel to every Creature, &amp;c. — And then after the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, had ſpoken to his Diſciples, he was received up into Heaven, and ſet down at the right Hand of God, — And now we who are the Believers in Chriſt Jeſus, and true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, we do live unto him, and if we dye, we dye unto the Lord, whether we live or die, we are the Lords; for this end Chriſt both died, revived, and roſe, that he might be Lord both of the Dead and of the Living; and he is Judg both of Quick and Dead, who is the only one Mediator betwixt God and Man, even the man Chriſt Jeſus, who makes interceſſion to God for his people, and is able to ſave to the utmoſt all that come to God by him, whoever lives to make Interceſſion for them, who is ſet down at the right Hand of God in Heaven, who is the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, who ſaid to <hi>John, I am the firſt and the laſt, I am he that Liveth, and was Dead, and behold I am alive for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Sultan Mahomet,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>I will perſue your Crucified God:</hi> wherein he is miſtaken, it was not the Eternal Incomprehenſible God, but Chriſt that was Crucified, and Died for his, and all mens Sins, if the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of the <hi>Turks</hi> will believe it, if not, he will die in his Sin: And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39868:8"/>
if he thinks to perſue Chriſt that was Crucified, he is like unto the <hi>Jewes</hi> that did crucifie him: But Chriſt is riſen from the Dead, and is alive, and dies no more, Death hath no more do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over him, nor hath <hi>Mahomet</hi> neither, and ſo is alive again, &amp; lives for evermore, and is ſet down in Heaven at the right Hand of God, out of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> reach to perſue, ſo is far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their vain Imaginations and Reach; and he that hath all power in Heaven and Earth given to him, who is the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, and King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and rules all Nations with a Rod of Iron, he is able to daiſh them to pieces, like a Potters Veſſel, and to abaſe the Pride of haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Men, and to ſave and deliver his People, out of the hands of the Deſtroyers, for he gives unto his Believers and Follower E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life; and Chriſt who laid down his Life for his Sheep, ſaid to the <hi>Jews, He had power to lay down his Life, and he had power to take it up again—This Commandment I have received of my Father,</hi> ſaith he, ſo it was not God his Father that Dyed; and Jeſus ſaid, <hi>His Sheep heard his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oice, and followed him,</hi> and ſaith he, <hi>I give unto them Eternal Life, and they ſhall never periſh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall any Man pluck them out of my Hand;</hi> and ſaith Chriſt, <hi>my Father that gave them me is greater then all, and no Man is able to pluck them out of my Fathers Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi> may ſee, that neither he nor the <hi>Jewes,</hi> nor no Man upon the Earth, is able to pluck Chriſts Sheep out of his Hands, Jeſus Chriſt ſaith ſo, who hath all power in Heaven and Earth given to him, and is the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, and King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. And your own <hi>Alcoran</hi> ſaith, <hi>that Jeſus will be a Witneſs in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them that obey not his Law, and do not believe in him;</hi> and here the Emperor may ſee, that Chriſt is able to defend his Sheep and ſave them; and none is able to pluck them out of his Hands, who ſaid, <hi>All power in Heaven and Earth is given unto me,</hi> who is ſet down in Heaven at the right Hand of God, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by his Spirit in his People, who knows his Heavenly Voice, diſtinct from the Voice of the Devil, and all his Angels, and all the natural Mens Voices upon the Earth, Chriſt Jeſus his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Voice is known, diſtinct from them all, who is above them all; and God and Chriſt may ſuffer or permit thee to deſtroy
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39868:8"/>
Hypocrites, &amp;c. But Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, thou nor no Man is able to pluck his Sheep out of his Hands, yea out of his Hand that was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified and is Riſen and Aſcended into Heaven, and ſits at the right Hand of God, thou haſt no power to pluck his Sheep out of his Hand, and therefore thou art not able, nor no Man: And therefore take heed of ſtriving againſt him that is too mighty for thee.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Sultan Mahomet</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> thou ſayeſt, <hi>Thou doeſt not fear the Wrath of their Crucified God,</hi> to wit the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as is ſaid before, God cannot be Crucified, but Chriſt Jeſus was Crucified according to the Fleſh, who is Riſen and Aſcended, and ſits at the right Hand of God; but hear, O <hi>Turk,</hi> what his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith of him, <hi>When the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhall be Revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels in Flaming Fire, taking Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting Deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his Power, when he ſhall be glorified in his Saints, and be admired by all them that believe who ſhall conſume the Wicked with the Spirit of his Mouth, and deſtroy them with the brightneſs of his coming,</hi> Hallelujah. And therefore let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that names the name of Jeſus, depart from Iniquity, for he hath born the Iniquities of us all, and makes an end of Sin, and Redeems us from Iniquity, and finiſhes Tranſgreſſion, who through his Death deſtroys Death that Sin brought, and the Devil the power of Death; and ſo there is no other name amongſt Men, given under the whole Heaven, whereby we muſt be ſaved, but by the name of Jeſus, which ſignifies a Saviour; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Prophet, <hi>A Virgin ſhall be with Child conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, and ſhall bring forth a Son, and they ſhall call his name</hi> Immanual, <hi>which by Interpretation is, God with us,</hi> ſo by his Son Jeſus Chriſt, God is with us, that God who was Speaker, and Teacher of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in Paradice, and as long as they kept under his teaching, they were happy, but when they forſook God's teaching and ſpeaking, and hearkened unto the Serpents ſpeaking and teaching, and followed it, they came into miſery, and his Poſterity, but according to the Promiſe of God to <hi>Adam, The Seed of the Woman is come, to bruiſe the Serpents Head,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, and he, namely Chriſt the Son of God, is the Saviour; and now in theſe laſt Dayes, God teaches us, and ſpeaks to us
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39868:9"/>
by his Son Chriſt Jeſus, whom God hath appointed to be heir of all things, by whom he made the World, the Heavens, and the Earth, and the Seas and all things therein, and ſo all the Children of the Lord are taught of the Lord, and in Righteouſneſs are they Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>And there are three which bear Witneſs or Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt; and theſe are one, and there are three which bear Record in Earth, the Spirit, the Water, and the Blood, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Blood of Chriſt which cleanſeth from all Sin, and the Water which waſheth from all filthineſs, and the Spirit to lead into all Truth, and Baptizes to Plung down Sin and Evil, and to Circumciſe to put off the body of Death, and Sins of the Fleſh, which is come into Man and Woman by Tranſgreſſion; and you muſt feel this Spirit in your hearts, which is a Witneſs for God who gives it you, which will be a witneſs for you or a witneſs againſt you: And you muſt feel the Blood of Chriſt ſprinkle your Conſciences, from your dead Works, that you may ſerve the living God, which Blood will be a witneſs for you, or a witneſs againſt you; and you muſt feel the Water of the Word to waſh you and cleanſe you, which will be a Witneſs for you or a Witneſs againſt you; ſo the Spirit of God, the blood of Jeſus, the Water of the Word, are three that agree in one, that bear Witneſs or Record in the Earth, and there are three which bear Witneſs or Record in Heaven, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one, he that hath an Ear to hear, let him hear,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Offence of one</hi> (to wit <hi>Adam,) Judgment came upon all Men to Condemnation, Even ſo by the Righteouſneſs of one,</hi> (to wit Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>the free Gift of God came upon all Men unto Juſtification of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son Jeſus Chriſt, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not Periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> And they that do believe in him have everlaſting Life, <hi>John,</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. Now <hi>concerning Gods Son, Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, he was made of the ſeed of</hi> David <hi>according to the Fleſh, and declared to be the Son of God, with power according to the Spirit of holineſs, by the Reſurrestion from the Dead, Rom.</hi> 1.3, 4.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:39868:9"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
